Guide to the Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters Oral History Collection OH.021
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters Oral History Collection
1988
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
OH.021
1.6 Linear Feet in 1 half manuscript box and 29 items within a shared cassette box and shared CD box
29 audiocassettes
The Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters was founded in the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan, New York in 1925 by A. Philip Randolph, Ashley L. Totten, W. H. Des Verney, and Roy Lancaster. The Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters Oral History Collection consists of audio recordings of interviews with Black people who worked as sleeping car porters and were members of the Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters. The interviews date from 1988 and include discussions of the narrators's family backgrounds, their emigrations from the southern United States (US) to the northern US, and their experiences working for the Pullman Company.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials found in collection; provenance is unknown. The accession number associated with this collection is 1950.093.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in alphabetical order by narrator's last name.
Historical Note
Manhattan, New York in 1925 by A. Philip Randolph, Ashley L. Totten, W. H. Des Verney, and Roy Lancaster. Those attending the meeting called for recognition of the Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters (BSCP) and the end of Pullman's Employee Representation Plan, a company union. It was not until 1936 that the BSCP received an international charter from the American Federation of Labor (AFL). A year later, the union took advantage of the apparatus of the new National Labor Relations Board and signed its first contract with the Pullman Company. This contract called for a 240-hour work month, a wage hike amounting to $1.25 million overall, job security, and union representation.
BSCP membership declined in the 1950s and 1960s as the railroad industry declined. With the rise of Amtrak in the early 1970s, the union experienced a brief resurgence until 1974 when Amtrak made a contract with the Hotel Employees and Restaurant Employees Union. The BSCP merged with the Brotherhood of Railway and Airline Clerks in 1978.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access CDs for some audiovisual materials in the collection are available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Other audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Scope and Contents
The Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters Oral History Collection consists of audio recordings of interviews with Black people who worked as sleeping car porters and were members of the Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters. The Berry Slater interview also includes an interview transcript. The interviews were conducted in 1988 in New York, New York; Chicago, Illinois; Denver, Colorado; and Los Angeles, California. The narrators discuss their family background, their migration from the southern United States (US) to the northern US, and their experiences working for the Pullman Company. The interviews cover race relations in the labor movement, segregation within the American Federation of Labor, and civil rights in the early to mid 20th century.
Oral history.; Audiocassettes.; Transcripts.; African Americans and labor unions; African Americans -- Civil rights -- United States; African Americans -- Economic conditions; Porters -- Labor unions -- United States.; Porters -- United States -- Interviews.; Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters
- Jewel Edward Brown, 1988-12-04
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 102, Audiocassette 12A-C)
- Esther Crawford, 1988-10-19
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 102, Audiocassette 8)
  - Access Copy (Box Shared Tamiment 122, Cd Crawford)
- Isiah Culbreath, 1988-10-19
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 102, Audiocassette 10)
- Israte Curtis, 1988-12-16
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 102, Audiocassette 7)
- Ish Flory, 1988-11-27; cuid489
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 102, Audiocassette 2A-B)
  - Access Copy (Box Shared Tamiment 122, Cd Flory)
- Harry Hawkins, 1988-10-18
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 102, Audiocassette 15)
- Robert Henderson, 1988-10-20
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 102, Audiocassette 9A-B)
- James Jackson, 1988-12-10
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 102, Audiocassette 11A-B)
- Amos Kimble, 1988-12-09
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 102, Audiocassette 5A-B)
- Elizabeth Lucas, 1988-09-02
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 102, Audiocassette 1)
  - Access Copy (Box Shared Tamiment 122, Cd Lucas (1-2))
- Elijah Shoemaker, 1988-12-27
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 102, Audiocassette 4A-C)
- Charles Simmons, 1988-10-15
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 102, Audiocassette 16A-B)
- Berry Slater, 1988-10-16
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 102, Audiocassette 14A-B)
  - Transcript (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Fred Smith, 1988-11-25
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 102, Audiocassette 3A-B)
- George Smith, 1988-12-12
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 102, Audiocassette 13A-B)
- Arthur Woolfolk, 1988-10-21
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 102, Audiocassette 6A-B)